hey guys and welcome to the long-awaited
credit repair video that I've been
promising you all for god knows how long
at this point anyways I have spent a lot
of time putting this together I took
some questions from you guys online and
I'm ready to get to this today so if
you're one of the people that asked the
question read it or I'm one of the
previous videos I really appreciate it
thanks for giving me some questions to
respond to and let's just jump into this
so credit repair how to build credit
from no credit or bad credit that's what
we're going to be discussing today first
and foremost if you haven't already
watched my previous videos on the
dispute process you might want to watch
those first and then come back to this
prerequisite shameless plug my name on
YouTube is 7/16 green if you're not
subscribed to my channel already
subscribe click the little notification
bell so that you're notified when I put
videos like this out this video on the
screen right here is part of the credit
repair playlist I have two videos here
the repair your credit score raise your
credit score in 30 days by yourself and
repair bad credit for free and 30 days
everything you'll ever need to know the
difference between these two videos the
first one is about 10 minutes long it's
a quick overview I guess is the best way
to put it the second video is 35 minutes
long very in-depth a lot of information
it kind of it explains everything you
need to know about credit I'm gonna go
over a lot of the same information in a
different way in this video but those
videos will be very helpful if you
haven't gone through the dispute phase
yet please check those out first and
foremost the most important thing that I
can tell you do not pay a credit repair
company you're more effective with your
own money and you are the only person
that is ever going to care about your
credit I mean that you can pay them to
pretend they care but no one's ever
going to care about your credit the way
you do your credit is better off in your
hands
and you are much more capable of
repairing or fixing your credit than
they are there's a lot of different ways
to look at it but there's no in my
opinion there's no reason to ever hire a
credit repair company and take it from
my experience I have hired a credit
repair company in the past biggest waste
of money ever actually the reason that
I'm so passionate on credit repair is
because the credit repair company that I
hired they screwed up and sent me the
letter that they meant to send to
TransUnion when I opened it and saw what
the dispute letter was comprised of I
was shocked how much money I was paying
this company for something I was very
very clearly able to do myself so what
what I would recommend here and of
course none of this is sponsored
material or anything like that but
credit Caramon it's my favorite tool I
think it's the easiest way to check your
credit now keep in mind that if you want
to see your full credit score and earned
sorry your full credit report you need
to go to annualcreditreport.com right
here this is the only place literally
the only place that you can get your
credit score it excuse me I keep saying
that your credit reports for free once a
year according to federal law you are
entitled to get a copy of all three of
your credit reports your credit report
do TransUnion your credit report through
Equifax and your credit report through
Experian credit card mod gives you your
credit scores from transunion and
equifax and it also gives you an
overview of your credit report although
Credit Karma
isn't technically your credit report
it's all the same information that's on
your credit report anyways there's very
little difference the reason there's one
of these signs over the Equifax logo I'm
sure you all know about the recent
Equifax breach that happened very
unfortunate affected about fifty percent
of all Americans which is insane
and it was
discovered or released a few days ago
that there was much more information
released than initially thought I think
in Equifax is just a dirty company all
the executives sold a whole bunch of
their shares before they reported this
problem to the public this is a
disgusting company now unfortunately you
can't choose to not use Equifax you're
stuck with these credit bureaus but
after what happened with a Koufax the
good news is that a lot of banks and
creditors have stopped using Equifax so
I would say don't even worry about
Equifax you can still get the
information on your credit report from
Equifax using credit karamja but
TransUnion that's what I use as my you
know the rule of thumb my basis whatever
you want to call it my TransUnion report
is the one that I care about it's the
one that I'm worried about and it's the
one that I follow the very simple reason
as TransUnion they're not expensive to
report to so from the agency side
collection agencies can report the
TransUnion fairly easily where it costs
more money and it's a little bit more
difficult to get approved to report to
Equifax or Experian now a lot of people
are worried about their FICO score
everyone knows the the word FICO a lot
of people what they don't know is that
it stands for the Fair Isaac corporation
that's what FICO is TransUnion Equifax
and Experian they all use what's called
vantage score I think they might be
advantaged score 4.0 by now maybe it's
still 3.0 I don't know it used to be 2.0
back when I back when I disputed
everything on my credit but I don't want
to get too far ahead of myself here my
TransUnion report is the only one that I
care about so no one that I worry about
because it's generally all encompassing
it has everything on there if I look at
my transunion credit report versus my
experience or my equifax credit report
there's generally nothing
on my Equifax Experian report that's not
already on TransUnion
TransUnion is great that's just my
personal opinion definitely check out
all three of your credit reports without
a doubt at least once a year check all
three of them make sure they're accurate
dispute whatever is not accurate again
if you want to learn how to dispute
anything watch my previous video as I
explained that all in depth so credit is
a catch-22 with no credit or bad credit
you can't gain new credit with no
positive credit your score continues to
stagnate good credit doesn't usually
project in a straight line it just needs
an upward trajectory creating better
credit usually involves taking small
hits for the greater good
so what do I mean by that as you can see
this green line the bright green line
this is the upward trajectory so January
February March April May June July I
just realize this is Jason Jaso on July
August September October November that's
interesting anyways so think of this as
your credit score and don't get your
expectations too high right off the bat
your your score is gonna go up and down
and up and down but overall you want an
upward trajectory well you can expect to
see is your score will go off when you
get granted a new line of credit or you
get a credit limit increase or something
like that or you pay off a balance if
you have student loans and you pay that
off in a balloon payment that's going to
significantly increase your credit score
now if you apply for a new credit card
and you have a hit on your your your
credit report a heart inquiry then you
might see a small drop on your credit
report now hard inquiries which I'll get
to in a little but they're very lightly
weighted they're they're not that big of
a deal
you can have a whole bunch of hard
inquiries and it's not gonna hurt your
credit score as much as a lot of other
things but in order to get good credit
you need to make little sacrifices here
you need to sacrifice two or three
points that you can get ten points two
months from now and that's the mentality
that you need to have don't get upset if
your score drops by a couple points as
long as it's for the greater good and as
long as you're seeing this overall
upward trajectory like in the freight
green line so high impact credit factors
these are the things that are going to
directly and most heavily impact your
credit score you've got your credit card
use which is high impact your payment
history high impact and draaga Tory
marks all high impact derogatory marks
our collections tax liens bankruptcies
civil judgments basically anything
negative is a derogatory market it means
exactly what it sounds like it means
credit card use let's go to this first
and just go over this now you might
recognize this these are screenshots
from Credit Karma
you're gonna see a few screenshots from
my credit card loan account I asked some
information not that I think there's
anything wrong with showing some
specific things like which credit cards
I have but I figured it would just be
better to uh to not give that
information out to a bunch of strangers
so don't take it personally I'm sure
you're all a bunch of nice people I only
took some selectively screenshots here
now just because I have 0% credit card
use doesn't mean that I don't have an
outstanding balance and I need my credit
cards it just means that I have enough
credit that my that my overall
utilization is 0%
so I'll get to that in a minute to I'll
show you how that works okay so hard to
make these videos at work anyways umm
where was I credit card use payment
history and derogatory marks let's take
a look at a spreadsheet here okay so
what we're going to talk about here is
your percent of credit used that's gonna
be your credit card use Oh easy of you
to swap back and forth here so credit
card use that's we're talking about here
percent of credit used now you have the
balance we're assuming that you have a
$500 balance and that you're carrying
that through from once a month not a
good idea
pay off your balances in full if
possible or as much as you possibly can
if you can't pay it off in full or a
large chunk at the very least pay the
minimum but I'm presenting these numbers
just because they're easy to work with
and it proves the point so let's say
that you have not any balance of $500
and your credit limit is $1,000 that's
50% credit card use as you can see over
here 50 to 74 percent is bad not as bad
as 75% or more but it's it's right up
there it's not good you don't want that
you want to keep that under 9% never
going to be able to get through this you
want to keep it between 0 and 9 percent
ideally 0% is the best ten to twenty
nine percent is okay thirty to forty
nine percent is you know I don't know
what I would call that I wouldn't call
it okay it's it's manageable maybe fifty
to seventy four percent is bad and 75
percent is very bad this is a high
impact variable so it's very important
that you have the lowest possible
percentage here because it's going to
have a high impact on your score so
again you have a $500 balance on a
thousand dollar credit limit that's 50
percent right there not a good number
now if you get this credit limit
increase from $1,000 to $2,000 suddenly
it drops down to 25% and those see were
25% brings you 25% is going to be right
here the the okay area now let's go back
to the other screen let's say that you
again get it doubled now you have a
$4,000 balance that's 12.5% if you solve
that 500
balance on the $4,000 available credit
it's over 500 our balance on $8,000
available credit that is six point two
five or six and a quarter percent six
point two five percent so that's
actually good that's great let's switch
over one more time you're gonna be in
this ideal area between zero and nine
percent so the whole time you cut the
same the same outstanding balance
you just have a larger credit limit and
now you're in this good healthy area
under nine percent so just something to
keep in mind if you can get your credit
limits increased that's great because
then you could spend more money and not
have it affect your your credit card
utilization your open credit utilization
is very very important if you have a
five hundred dollar balance on sixty
four thousand dollars of available
credit it's going to be 0.72 I'm sure
you all remember from math class and
first grade or somewhere around that
area it runs up because it's over 0.5 so
this is going to be 1% over on this
screen that's going to show up as one
percent utilization now if you have 128
thousand dollars in credit this point
three nine percent is going to brown
down this is going to be zero percent so
and then just to be clear I don't have
anywhere near 128 thousand dollars worth
of available credit but I do have a
balance right now it just so happens I
have enough available credit that even
though I carried a balance from last
month to to this one a small balance
granted it's still at 0% on paper so
something to be mindful of you always
want to get the highest possible credit
balances that you can one important
thing that I'm going to say is
self-control is a big thing
if you have $20,000 of available credit
and you don't trust yourself to manage
$20,000 because you got this credit and
it feels like free money if you don't
trust yourself with $20,000 in credit
then don't allow the credit card company
to give you $20,000 in credit I'm
assuming that if you're watching this
video you're probably having trouble
obtaining credit so we're gonna get
there just just keep that in mind I got
very nervous when I was approved for a
credit card and they gave me what at the
time I thought was a ridiculous amount
of credit but you know now it's my
favorite credit card I paid off in full
every single month no issues I don't
spend more than I can afford to spend
and it's great for my credit score my
credit score is fantastic that's one of
the reasons that I can carry a small
balance or month to month and keep my
credit card used at 0% but if you don't
trust yourself with 20,000 30,000 40,000
dollars worth of credit don't let the
bank's give it to you that is credit
suicide if you let them give you more
credit then you can reasonably manage
the next high impact factor is payment
history it shows that I have 100%
payment history then every single
payment I've made has been on time what
I want you to notice here is how close
these numbers are a hundred percent is a
hundred percent it's perfect that's
that's good that's what you want 99
percent is okay I need a percent not so
good 97 percent is bad
under 97% is very bad excuse me
good afternoon
where were we 100% great 99% okay 98%
not so great 97% bad under 97% very bad
so you can see there's not much margin
for error there you really have to have
a good payment history now as you can
see underneath the payment history this
is a snapshot from a student loan that I
had back in 2009 that as you can tell I
didn't really take care of it very well
just to give you some context back in
2000 now 2011 my credit was terrible
we're talking about like under 500 I
just didn't have the money to pay back
my student loans I didn't have a good
job at the time you know it wasn't a
good time for me my credit was hit hard
and credit is like money you can blow
through a lot of money really quickly
but then to make money it's a lot of
hard work
credit operates much in the same way but
as you can see back then in 2010 a
couple of my payments were made on time
these blank spots here and this is what
it looks like it's always a grid when
they when the creditors report your
payment history they report it and they
great just like this so you can see in
2010 they didn't even record it a few of
the month they reported on April May
June they didn't report it in July or
August they did report it in September
October they didn't report it in
November December January February March
were in 2011 now we have a couple
payments that were fine apparently in
April of 2011 that's when I stopped
making
payments that's what my credit report
would state at least I had this
information fixed or I should say taken
off of my credit report because when I
paid off the account in fall in 2013 I
then disputed the information at that
point in time the creditor was already
paid back they didn't care about my
dispute so they're not gonna continue to
validate the debt after a disputes been
filed so I think that that should make
sense you if you don't really understand
what I mean by that again watch the the
other videos and the credit repair
playlist it explains that concept a
little bit better but the student loan
company the company that loaned me that
money they don't care if the credit
bureaus are hitting my credit score
because they've already been paid back
they don't have any more interest in
hurting my credit score so when I
disputed the payment history the late
payment history they just they went
ahead and took it off it was as simple
as writing one dispute letter and they
removed it you see there's one time
where it's 90 days late and then 120
days late and that goes on and on until
it's caught back up you can see that
there's 90 to 119 days late and 120 to
149 days late other clarifications that
they use don't worry your accounts going
to default if you can help it if it does
happen and it's out of your control try
to get it paid before 30 days if you
can't get the 30 days try to get it paid
in 60 days if you can't get it paid in
60 days get it paid under 90 days once
you get into that 90 days that's when
it's really gonna start to affect your
score bad no I have another spreadsheet
here that I'm going to use to to show
you an example of this so this is
payment history let's say that you have
12 total payments and out of those 12
payments you've only made two of them on
time so you have ten late payments now
your percent of on time
payments is 16.6 70% that's terrible
your your so far below that 97%
unacceptable rate that it's gonna feel
hopeless now with each passing month
let's say that you're not making
payments this number is going to
continue to drop 11 late payments out of
13 total payments that's 15 percent 12
late payments out of 14 total payments
that's fourteen point two nine percent
you get the point this will continue to
drop and drop and drop now let's see
what happens if you stop at 13 you get
you get your act together
now we're gonna continue making our
payments on time so late payments are
gonna stay at 13 but this number 12
payments is going to continue to
increment so let's go ahead and drag
this down you know that didn't work how
I thought it would okay so now 13 out of
23 payments worth 43% so I'd imagine
you're probably thinking it's gonna take
me years to get back to that 97 percent
what you want to do in this type of
situation is you want to get as many
open credit lines as possible we're
gonna talk about the different types of
credit that you can get with no credit
or bad credit later on towards the end
of this video but this this example that
I'm showing you here with the 13 late
payments this right here is under the
pretense that you're only making one
payment every month so you have one
account you're making one payment so now
let's say that you have the 13 late
payments but now instead of one account
that you need to pay every month let's
say you have three accounts so now it's
incrementing from 15 to 18 18 to 21 21
to 24 24 to 27 27 to 30 30 to 33 you get
the point so now we're at 66.67% let's
say that you have four accounts instead
of instead of three I mean I I think you
see where it's going at this point
that's not right so I mean we're talking
about a matter of one two three four
five six seven eight months you already
got it back up to 71% not not great not
ideal but you can keep this up and the
more accounts that you have if you have
five accounts six accounts and you're
making at least your minimum payment on
time every month then I mean you're
gonna be in good shape in a matter of a
year but all this takes patience
remember patience is a virtue your
credit score you might have destroyed it
overnight but it's gonna take a little
bit of time to repair the majority of
the damage can be fixed by doing a few
rounds of dispute letters the first
round to take care of the bulk of it the
second round will get a couple leftover
things but at that point you have a good
idea of who's actively reporting to the
credit bureau and which debts are valid
and active stilling collections whatever
the case is so you you just need to be
patient and make your payments on time
but it's very easy to stop making
payments and for that number you can get
this all the way off until it's it's
right at that you know 97 98 99 percent
and then you start missing payments
young especially if you have six open
accounts or you know five four open
accounts whatever it is if you stop
making payments on those accounts it's
gonna drop quicker than it it went off
so something to be mindful of that's the
reality of the situation it's it's not
fortunate it's not ideal but that's how
it is the next thing that we're going
to talk about is dragon Tori marks if
you haven't accounting collections and
this drives me crazy
I own a collection agency there's so
many videos on YouTube saying you don't
have to pay collection agency is okay
you don't have to pay collection
agencies but there's a lot of collection
agencies that are going to file a civil
judgment against you and get their money
back in court if you don't repay them if
if you're dealing with an agency that's
not going to take you to court for
whatever reason maybe they're too small
they don't have their resources maybe
that that is insignificant they don't
really care you and your family and your
associates and your neighbors are gonna
be getting calls regularly and this is
gonna go on for years now one thing that
I hear all the time we contact someone
even on a debt that's two weeks old
freshly charged off we call someone
about the debt and they say well it
sounds like a scam I've heard about the
scam on the news and these people know
very well that they just took out this
loan a couple weeks ago and we can quote
it for them we tell exactly what the
balances were that they they took it out
the location they took it out the bank
account number that they used all this
information could verify their stones a
scary number the date of birth with them
and they'll tell us it's a scam I don't
think that they really believe it's a
scam I just think that there's a lot of
people that really believe that they
don't need to repay their debt it's
unfortunate that people think that way
but let's just get this out of the way
cooperate with collection agencies you
know what happens if you don't pay that
first collection agency they sue you for
the balance you get a default judgment
against you or your account gets sold to
a more aggressive collection agency then
we're aggressive clock changin see
harasses you they sue you or they sell
it to an even more aggressive collection
agency once you get to the third fourth
fifth agency down that list your
relatives are sick of you you've already
had to change their phone number a few
times because you're losing sleep over
these phone calls and the agency that
has your diet and I hate to say it but
there are some bad apples there are some
agencies that you don't want to have
access to your information the longer
you go without paying a diet the more
easily accessible its gonna be to the
open market the the unlicensed agencies
that purchase your debt on the internet
for pennies on the dollar if you pay it
as soon as you possibly can and it's
higher off that chain of title you're
going to be dealing with more legitimate
agency so don't push it off I don't know
what makes people think they don't have
to pay collection agency is like I said
you don't have to pay collection
agencies but it's definitely not in your
best interest to not pay collection
agencies if any of you are dealing with
the collection agency and you want some
advice you want some guidance you want
to know how to how to deal with it let
me know you know ask me write it ask me
in the questions down below shoot me an
email I'm happy to let you know the
reality of the situation and I'm gonna
go through a sample debt portfolio and
show you the information that the
collection agencies have now keep in
mind what I'm gonna be showing you isn't
an actual debt portfolio because I can't
show you people's names and Social
Security numbers and addresses it's all
fictional information it was completely
created for the sake of this video but I
think you'll find it interesting
especially if you're not in this
industry so let's move on past
collections paid collection agencies at
least cooperate with them the collection
agencies report to the credit bureaus so
you want to keep them happy if you can't
pay them ask for a forbearance
especially with something like student
loans sometimes you can work out a
forbearance with them or a difference
whatever you want to call it they'll
give you an entire year where they won't
report any delinquency is sometimes the
six months lens is three months but
they'll give you some time to get your
life back on track without letting the
account get into war standings so ask
for that at the very least excuse me
okay so back to business here
bankruptcies if you filed for bankruptcy
you're going to it's gonna haunt you for
seven years there's no you know there's
no sugarcoating it a bankruptcy is going
to severely impact your credit it's not
completely unmanageable if you have to
file bankruptcy file bankruptcy
certainly don't make it your first
choice it's it's not a good option
unless it's your only option let's say
that you dug yourself in so deep there's
just no climbing out of that hole if you
qualify for bankruptcy you qualify for
bankruptcy it's up to the courts but you
want to avoid bankruptcy at all cost
a civil judgment let's say for example
you owe a collection agency some money
you refuse to pay them you dock their
calls they they serve you with some
papers or they don't serve you with
papers I'm sure you can find plenty of
news articles and hear about the nasty
tricks of the trade which we don't
partake in here but I have heard of
agencies that intentionally use
loopholes that allow them to obtain
default judgments against the debtors
without even having them properly
notified about the debt but again if you
if you pay your debts if you work with
the agencies that type of stuff doesn't
happen to you if you have judgments
civil judgments I believe that's public
record you can see it on your credit
report all the information is going to
be on your credit report you can you can
pay judgments off in fact you should pay
judgments off and then they get removed
from your credit report if not removed
at least they're indicated that they're
paid off they show up is a zero balance
under judgments so if your credit report
is pulled a creditor might be able to
see that you had a judgment against you
but also see that it was paid off after
so many years it falls off your credit
report just like a bankruptcy it
depending on what state you're in 7 to
10 years that bankruptcies off your
credit report but even two years after
filing bankruptcy you could have your
card
work back up to a reasonable number 6:40
is the magic number
6:40 is where you can start obtaining
unsecured credit but you want to shoot
for 650 because things have changed in
the past few years 650 is the real magic
number 640 is the magic number you know
technically but I would say don't waste
your hard inquiries applying for credit
cards with a flat 640 that's that now
also you can see down here when
delinquencies are reported to the credit
bureaus they see it like this 30 60 90
days late it all obviously goes up to
120 and past 120 it's just severely
delinquent and it will really really
bring your score down okay like I said
several times you want to keep your
score up to 100% payment history so you
can see I have a 100% payment history
but you can also clearly see that even
just a few years ago I had severely
delinquent accounts so there is hope
credit age this is very interesting
I I did mask the names of my credit
cards again I don't think there's
anything wrong with showing it to people
but I would just prefer not to I feel
like there's a little bit of privacy to
be had now as you can see this is a
screenshot from Credit Karma
my first credit card right here has a
terrible APR but this credit card was
open nine years and four months ago the
only reason this credit card is still
open is because I need that line of
credit I need that credit card to keep
my credit aged at a reasonable place now
as you could tell between nine years and
four months ago when I was you know
young Dom and whatever the expression is
I applied for credit and I wasn't I
wasn't capable of maintaining it it was
it was irresponsible for me to apply for
a credit card when I was that young but
I applied I was granted a credit card
which is
because so many people apply and they
can't get approved for credit cards
these days because of a lack of credit
history now this credit card company was
happy to give me a credit card you know
right on my birthday
basically anyways terrible APR but
there's no annual fee so I don't use
this credit card but I keep it you know
locked up in the bank vault it's there
for an emergency if I need it but at
this point all I'm doing is hanging on
to it for the credit age now my next two
credit cards between two years and one
year and ten months ago so around the
same around the same time frame this as
you can tell is about two years ago is
when I got my credit score up to that
650 range finally so I would describe
one of those cards as being a luxury
card the brand of you know the bank the
brand is something that you associate
with luxury you can probably figure out
what it is and then there's what I would
call my general purpose credit card now
I had both of these credit cards
assigned to specific scenarios so for
example I would have all of my bills go
on to this card my general purpose card
and then when I went out to went out to
dinner went to restaurants I used my
luxury card because the the luxury card
as it were has it has specific benefits
for card holders when you use it at a
restaurant double points cash back you
know how that goes no we're two years
one year and 10 months ago now we have
the emergency use credit card it's a
decent card but it's hard to pay the
reason it's hard to pay is because the
bank that that credit card is issued
through I don't have one within 100
miles of where I live I applied for it
because I like the bank I use the bank
for something specific I want to get
into details that you watch but I use
the bank I really like them I applied
for a credit card through them while
my credit was good I was at this point
as you can see this period of time I was
just applying for as much credit as I
could get sorry I need to advance that I
figured my my credit score is good let's
get as much credit as I can and then
wait two years cuz I don't mind driving
up my hard inquiries they're gonna fall
off after two years now after getting
this credit card with a pretty good
credit limit I realized it was hard to
pay because the only way to really pay
them is to have a checking account with
that same Bank now at the time I had a
business checking account with that Bank
but it was a personal credit card you
can't pay off a personal credit card
with a business checking account I mean
you can but your accountant isn't gonna
be happy with you it's also not not a
good practice business's business
personal is personal so I I call that my
emergency use credit card if I need to
use it I will but I have to jump through
hoops to repay that credit card it's a
flaw with that particular bank they
don't make it easy to pay off I think
it's incentive to try to get you to bank
with them also but it's in my person in
my opinion it's just bad business now I
have this Amazon rewards credit card and
my favorite credit card both of them are
issued through the same bank what
happened was I was ordering through
Amazon I get everything from Amazon
everything from groceries to video games
you name it I get it from Amazon clothes
the shirt might be from Amazon probably
is from Amazon
I love Amazon so I got an Amazon rewards
credit card because they give you 5%
cash back on anything that you purchased
from Amazon or at least anything that's
Prime so 5% cash back that's crazy I get
so much cash back from them it's insane
five percent is great and I think there
was an introductory offer where it was
double cash back so he's getting like
10% cash back for a couple months when I
got approved for that card it was just
outrageous still it's one of the best
credit cards that I have now
after using that credit card
specifically with Amazon for so long it
didn't have very many benefits outside
of Amazon so I like the bank I can tell
you that much I love the bank that
issued that card I just didn't want to
use my Amazon card I didn't want to
swipe that card but I went out for
groceries so I applied for another
credit card with that same Bank
I was approved for that and it is to the
same my favorite credit card
forget the luxury brands of credit cards
you know sometimes just the you know the
well-established banks have the best
incentives the reason this is my
favorite credit card is because yeah I'm
not I'm making a video the reason that I
went to the to that Bank is because
they're one they're reputable too I love
that they service my Amazon account and
they did such a great job but
specifically its 1.5% cash back on
everything so I can spend this car I can
use this card when I'm buying groceries
I could use it for gas I could use it to
pay my taxes and I get 1.5% cash back on
everything now there's specific things
they give you 3% cashback like
restaurants for example so look at the
benefits of any card when you're when
you're planning in getting a credit card
see what the benefits are for all of the
credit cards that you work with or that
you have the ability to apply for and
definitely don't waste your hard
inquiries on credit cards that don't
have good incentives if you travel a lot
you might want to travel credit card I
don't travel very often I'm not I'm not
one for airplanes so I like the cashback
and the the point cards that give you
incentives
I love Amazon so a lot of credit cards
these days give you Amazon gift cards
that you can buy with points there's
just so much free money if you use your
credit card instead of a debit card to
buy everything for an entire year you
get at least one percent maybe 1.5%
anywhere from one to three percent cash
back on every single purchase you make
even 5% in some cases I mean it's free
money why not do it I haven't used cash
or a debit card in years now all I use
is credit cards to pay for everything I
also pay off my credit card bill several
times a month I'll get to that later in
the video but I like to have a zero
balance carried over every single month
this right here these bottom two you can
see seven months and one month old this
is these are both issued through the
same bank but these are specialty lines
of credit this one right here was a
big-ticket item I needed to buy
something that was expensive I didn't
feel like draining my savings to buy it
so I got a specific line of credit and
again I don't want to get too much into
detail with it but that same bank also
issues medical credit cards so I had a
medical procedure I needed recently that
wasn't covered by my insurance it was
very expensive again I didn't want to
drain my savings so I got that medical
credit card through the same bank that
issues this electronics company I guess
you could say credit card and now I have
these two credit cards as you did the
same Bank it's an up-and-comer it's
really been a hit on my credit age now
there's this company called final you
can see it down here
finally incorporated they shut down I
love this bank it was so cool you could
generate a brand new card number and set
parameters for it so you could say I
need a new Visa card number that will
only work for three months and it will
only work on this website or I want a
card that expires after one month or I
want a card for a one-time use it was a
great card for buying things online and
again they had they had great incentives
to that a good cash back program I
believe they were bought out and that's
why they went out of business it's not
that I think they failed I'm pretty sure
they were actually bought out but final
was a great company now I had this card
for I think about two years so when they
closed that down it lowered my average
credit age or at least it impacted it
negatively in some way now I want you to
take a look at this this is interesting
let's go back over to the spreadsheet
here credit age you might notice that my
credit age doesn't exactly make sense
you see two years and one month right
here now the reason for that let's take
a look at this these are the cards I
have them labeled the same way I do over
on that PowerPoint or who will slides
presentation there's the the first
credit card the luxury car the general
purpose whatever this is how many years
and how many months they've been open
for now the one thing that's not
factored in over here is my auto loan I
have an auto loan that's eight months
old so what I've done is I've converted
the years a month just in two months
here I've then taken the average which
comes out to be 25 that's the average of
all of these months put together so you
multiply them all together and then you
divide it by the amount of in this case
lines of credit so my average credit
length is 25 months which is 2.08 years
so if we take a look over at what Credit
Karma or TransUnion in this case is
saying two years and one month yep that
makes sense two years and one one that's
exactly what this tells me here so now
let's do something interesting let's say
that I close out this medical credit and
this big ticket item here let's say that
I I closed those out they're no longer
open credit so now my credit each goes
from two years and one month to a little
bit over two and a half
let's say that I paid my auto loan off
let's say that my auto loan off entirely
as well as my medical credit card and
this big ticket item credit card excuse
me good afternoon we're a collection
agency people call us and just press
buttons in the phone like they just want
to see how we answer the phone what's
the name of the company is
I just hate out dishonest people or just
call us and say you know I I saw this on
my credit report I would like to know
what's going on but I don't want to get
too off track um so where was I here so
let's say that I pay off my auto loan I
close out this big ticket item credit
card and I finished paying off this
medical credit card and those are all
paid off
I closed those accounts now suddenly
it's up to just about three years on the
other side on the other hand let's say
that I close this first credit card that
I ever had let's close that out now I'm
down to one point one eight years or
fourteen months one year and two months
that's horrible that is that's almost
cut in half than what I have right now
which is already bad so this credit card
right here this is my Savior so get a
credit card as early as soon as possible
and hang on to it
don't let it get close don't let it
default don't let it go into collections
keep that card open as soon as possible
if you don't have a credit card right
now get one as soon as possible if
you're on this video because you can't
get a credit card then we'll take care
of that don't worry about it just yet
because I'm gonna walk you through that
a little bit but establishing a good
length of credit is very very important
let's do one more thing for example I I
use the Amazon rewards card but I don't
use this emergency used card I I love
that this
my favorite credit card but I can
replace that with either row four or
five the luxury or the general-purpose
because they're comparable they're very
similar
I could technically get rid of these I
can delete all of those lines of credit
or not delete but close them out now I'm
up to three three years a little bit
over three years I pay off my auto loan
and I'm I'm nearing four years at this
point so that I mean that's something
that you need to be mindful of you know
you don't want to close a credit card
that you've had open for a significant
period of time because it's helping you
more than you realize
don't forget that this is if we can take
a look back over here this is medium
impact so it's not as high impact as
credit card use or open credit
utilization payment history or dragon
story marks but it is the next most
important factor after that so now you
can see up here it's really bad if it's
under two years between two to four
years is also pretty bad five to six
years is good seven to eight years is
good nine or more years is excellent so
if I really really wanted to you know
get to get this to look nice I could pay
off my auto loan close out all of my
credit cards except this very first one
and now I've got over nine years and I'm
gonna be looking good as far as this
credit age is concerned or I can just be
patient hang on to everything that I
have maybe close the medical credit line
once I'm done paying off the balance I
currently have on there but you get how
that works it's it's you gotta make
sacrifices you have to figure out what
works for you low impact factors these
don't really
fact your credit score as much as you
might think you need to know where you
can take a hit my total accounts for
example I've got nine open accounts five
closed accounts
that's 14 total accounts now open and
closed accounts what this takes into
account is credit cards auto loans
student loans other loans which would be
like I I think I have or at least had an
account it was a just a line of credit
through a bank like a personal that
consolidation type of loan I never
actually used it I just opened it to
have it in case I ever wanted to use it
and then I left the bank and closed it
you know kind of pointless it was there
it counted as an account I don't have 14
open accounts right now but as you as
you saw most of my open accounts are
credit cards even though I only use one
of them on a daily basis maybe three of
them total you know I have nine open
credit cards and just by keeping them
locked up in the safe at the bank
Security vault my you know my credit
score is doing nice because of that a
home equity line of credit or a mortgage
or sometimes reported to the credit
bureaus sometimes they're not it depends
if it's a private loan it depends if
it's a federal loan it depends on a lot
of factors but that you can't guarantee
that it is or isn't going to be on your
credit report it that depends on you
that depends on who you go through what
what type of company they are ask them
about their policies and procedures for
credit reporting it might be good to
have you know let's say for example you
need more accounts you need more on-time
payments to get your credit score off
it's going to help you to have a home
equity line of credit or a mortgage
account that you're making a monthly
payment on overall the more accounts you
have and the more often or not even more
often but the more responsible you are
with those accounts your credit is going
to match
get good as long as you take good care
of it forget about the home equity line
of credit in the mortgage that's
sometimes it's there sometimes it's not
but credit cards auto loan student loans
and other loans which is pretty much any
other type of loan except for payday
loans now that depends on the collection
agency if you have a payday loan the
collections in C can report it to the
credit bureaus
but generally the actual creditor
doesn't so it depends what type of line
of credit you have but some are reported
to the credit bureaus some aren't it's
expensive to report debt to the credit
bureaus so a small agency one with maybe
20 collectors they might not report your
debt to the credit bureaus but you might
have someone else might have that same
debt that just happened to end up with a
different agency that has 500 employees
a much larger agency and they might have
a contract with TransUnion to actively
report credit card inquiries as you can
see you know I'm a business owner
and I have a thing for credit cards
you've seen all the credit cards I have
just inside of this one year but owning
a business has definitely taken a toll
on my credit just starting up a business
from you know from the ground up my
credit my credit was already bad when I
started the business and it just got
worse and worse and worse until I
actively started working on it hard
inquiries fall off after two years have
a two year plan if you want to buy a
house and you want to buy a house this
year or next year try to keep the hard
inquiries down if if you want to buy a
house two or three years from now have
as many hard inquiries as you want
they're not good they're weighted so
lightly that it's not gonna kill you
just like the total accounts zero to
five isn't good six of ten isn't good 11
to 20 is good and 21 or more is great
but all in all this doesn't have that
much impact on your credit
anyways hurt inquiries get them all out
of the way early open as many lines as
you cry of credit as you can
young so that those hard inquiries fall
off by the time you're ready to buy a
house have a two year plan notice the
brackets here if I move the mouse it's
going to cover it up but there's zero
hard inquiries that's the best number
that you can have and then there's one
to two hard increse you're in a bracket
three to four hard inquiries you're in a
bracket five eight hard inquiries you're
in a bracket and nine or more hard
inquiries you're in a bracket so hard
inquiry number one three five and nine
are harmful hard inquiries number two
four seven or Tanana are less so less
harmful so weigh the pros and cons one
of the questions that I got and I'll get
there in just a minute excuse me
yes so one of the questions that I got
was should I take the hard inquiry and
get a credit line increase or should I
avoid the hard inquiry and prevent the
credit line increase now you need to
weigh the pros and cons there you know
your credit situation better than anyone
else I mean I can take a look at your
credit report and I could let you know
what I think is in your best interest
but when it comes down to it you know
what's what's best for you you know what
your plans are that's why I say they
have a two year plan at the very least
know what the next two years of your
life are going to look like and know
what you want that third year after that
to look like I personally think that the
average person should be looking about
five years ahead into the future when it
comes to finances at least have an idea
of where you want to be financially five
years from now but again I'm going off
on a tangent I don't want to I don't
want to get there right now because
that's not what this video is about so
there's some myths I'm sure that plenty
of you have heard these myths I think
they're all very harmful myths it's good
to carry a balance no false it is not
good to carry a balance ever it's okay
to
Karia small balance but you are always
better carrying no balance
I've heard people justify it like well
if you're not using your credit at least
a little bit you're not profitable to
the banks that are issuing you the
credit so why would it be in their best
interest to help your credit score well
there's there's a fallacy with that
logic and that is that the point of your
credit score is to indicate to the
creditors how likely you are to repay
other creditors if you pay off your
balance in full every single month on a
credit card account you're showing the
creditors that you are capable of
repaying creditors on time in full
without fail so it is not good to carry
a balance in fact it is good to carry no
balance if you have eight credit cards
nine credit cards whatever if you have a
lot of credit cards like I do and as
soon as the statement period ends for
those credit cards are all at zero and
you have a 0% 0% credit utilization that
is where you're gonna see the best
increase on your credit report but
you're going to see the most positive
results that way so it is not good to
carry a balance there's only one credit
score false that's not true
there is actually three credit bureaus
it depends how you look at it there's
actually more like five credit bureaus
but the main ones Experian Equifax and
TransUnion and then there's the Fair
Isaac corporation or FICO FICO has their
algorithm that they used to determine a
credit score and then Equifax Experian
and TransUnion all use some variation of
vantage score I believe I said at the
beginning of the video that it's
vantagescore three or four that they're
using it was vantagescore two back when
I was filing my disputes on my credit
but there are a lot of different credit
scores I personally choose to go by what
TransUnion
sighs because TransUnion is so widely
used if I apply for a credit card I
generally see it hit my transunion
credit report in the form of a hard
inquiry before it hits any of the other
ones if it hits any of the other ones
for that matter so there's plenty of
credit scores make sure you at least
know what they all say make sure you
know what all of your credit reports say
but know that you have a lot of
different credit reports a lot of
different credit scores if you have a
640 credit score or a 650 and you think
you should be getting approved for
unsecured credit make sure you check
your other credit scores so that you're
not shocked when you get denied and find
out that you have a 639 with Experian or
I don't even want to talk about FICO
right now because they're so off the
charts they're so different and not many
companies actually use them anymore if I
go it's more common in the home equity
line or mortgage world but even there
we're seeing VantageScore based systems
used more often these days so know all
of your credit scores and what take a
look at all of your credit reports know
what's going on with your credit there's
a lot of scores there's a lot of reports
you need to check them all out
individually married couples share a
credit score false they don't share a
credit score they might have shared
credit and one spouse doing something
negative can impact the other spouses
credit if they have shared accounts but
they don't share a single credit score
paying debts remove some no pain deaths
does not remove them paying debts will
report the account is paid in full or
settled in full after a certain amount
of time it will fall off your credit
report I believe I believe it depends on
the state you're in actually where where
I live at 7 years it's a single statute
of limitations different states have
different statute of limitations for
filing legal action regarding and debt
it's the same thing with what falls off
your credit report after how long just
like a bankruptcy a bankruptcy my stand
seven to ten years based on what state
you're in but yeah I mean that's that
painted that doesn't remove it only time
or a little bit hanging a dot will just
make it reflect in a positive way
instead of a negative way and your
credit report you don't owe it that if
it's not on your report that's false
there's plenty of debt out there in the
world that people all with it isn't
reported to the credit bureaus just
because it's not reported the credit
bureaus doesn't mean that they don't owe
it you can be stupid for a debt that
hasn't been reported to the credit
bureaus so if you're gonna call from a
collection agency and they're trying to
clock on a debt and you don't see it on
your you don't see it on your credit
report pay the agency as long as it's
legitimate you know what that supe
obtained it's pretty easy to track the
debt down if you're if you're told that
you owe a debt for a Victoria's Secret
credit card call Victoria's Secret
follow the chain of title figure out who
they sold it to just it's not on your
credit report doesn't mean you don't owe
it and it doesn't mean that you can't be
sued for it what else do we have here
credit repair companies can do more than
you can not true that is the biggest
misconception that one drives me nuts
you are so much more capable of managing
your credit score than a credit repair
company if you watch the longer of the
two videos that I put up on credit
repair and and filing your credit
disputes there's a phone call where I
call a credit repair agency I have it on
speakerphone before I call them I
explain how they operate I asked some
questions the guy basically corroborates
exactly what I told you the viewers
ahead of time that someone asked me in
the question is it a scam so I guess
we'll get to that in a minute
is it a scam I think so I probably
shouldn't say that but yes I think
they're scams technically speaking a lot
of them actually will get your credit
score off but please don't pay them
please please please don't pay them I
would prefer to personally help you then
for you to go pay somebody and I won't
charge you anything oh let's see
income or demographic
affects credit no it doesn't your income
and your demographic do not affect your
credit the only thing that your income
is going to affect is your ability to
repay credit but don't spend what you
can't afford to repay don't think of a
credit card is being cashed it's not
cashed don't spend cash that you don't
have to spend and if you're going to if
you're going to use credit to buy
something that's outside of the rom of
what you can afford make sure that you
can structure a plan to repay it that
but as I'm saying the only thing that
income has to do with credit is your
ability to repay it having a better job
doesn't affect your credit score which
is the next one about our job equals a
better credit score not true your job
does not affect your credit score if
you're applying for a job some places
will actually hole your credit score
they have to ask for your permission
obviously but some places will check
your credit and that will be a factor
and whether or not you get the job
now some more misconceptions closing a
credit card will improve your score as
we saw closing a credit card as we saw
right over here yeah it can it can
positively impact certain things so
that's just jumped up from two point
whatever to three three and a half years
so yes it can positively impact it in a
certain way but closing a credit card
does not improve your score or as a
general rule let's say for example I
closed these two right here it jumps
from 2.0 eight years to 1.0 six years
that's bad so it can or it can help or
can hurt it make sure you know which
direction you're taking it by closing
that account you can't recover from the
bankruptcy that's false
you can't recover from a bankruptcy it
takes time it takes energy it takes hard
work it takes budgeting it takes
discipline it takes self-respect but you
can recover from a bankruptcy but try to
avoid a bankruptcy at all costs if you
have to file bankruptcy just remain
hopeful because you can recover you just
need to reform a little
that's do not need to be paid false
that's Junie be paid that's the point of
dots I've been watching Judge Judy
lately and she rips people apart when
they think that they're entitled to not
repay their debts that's just the world
we live in a contract is a contract I
can't tell you how many times a day my
collectors hear on the phone I don't
need to repay that because I didn't
physically sign anything you know what
it's 2018 an electronic signature is a
signature you think that if you apply
for an American Express card online and
you get approved and you rack up $10,000
on that IMAX card you think Animax isn't
going to sue you and when just because
you didn't physically sign a piece of
paper that's not the way the world works
that's you need to be paid the YouTube
videos that you see where people saying
you don't need to pay collection
agencies you don't need to pay creditors
I guarantee those people don't have the
credit score that they would probably
like to have and if they do have a
somewhat decent credit score it's mostly
a result of gaming the system if
somebody is on YouTube and they're
encouraging you to not pay your debts I
think that says more about the person
than it does the system to be honest
what does it say about your integrity if
you think it's okay to borrow from
people and not repay them just because
it's a bank doesn't mean it's okay to
not pay them just because the bank is
worth millions or billions of dollars
doesn't mean it's not okay to pay them
you borrow money you pay it back that's
the world we live in
that's our economy we would have a much
better economy if people weren't in so
much dad if people can manage their
finances better if you can't afford to
live in a $300,000 house don't find it
$300,000 our house you know I mean it's
it to me it sounds so simple it's not so
stupid but if you search collection
agency on YouTube you'll find thousands
of videos of deadbeats
you know people that look like I don't
even want to get into it but people that
you know aren't exactly corporate
executive
credit experts telling you you don't
need to pay clock genes and Caesar you
don't need to repay debts forget about
them they're not giving you good
information that's bad advice so what's
the harmful math building credit from no
credit or bad credit this is supposed to
be the crux of the video so to speak so
building credit from no credit or bad
credit 640 is the magic number shoot for
650 you might have a 640 with one credit
bureau and then have a 6:30 or 6:20 with
another credit bureau so make sure you
check all of your credit scores 640 is
the number in which creditors will start
giving you unsecured credit unsecured
just means that you don't have
collateral held against it and we'll get
to what a secured credit card is in a
minute because it's very important
forget FICO news VantageScore everyone
in the world they must use a Santas
score I think FICO is antiquated at this
point I really don't see FICO being used
for much of anything but I'd all those
credit repair message boards online it's
crazy how many people are obsessed with
FICO your FICO score is so it just it
doesn't matter discover actually if you
have a Discover card you have free
access to your FICO score at any time
but discovery doesn't even use your FICO
score to approve you for their credit
cards they use vantagescore as a vantage
score model so it's kind of crazy the
FICO is antiquated it's good to know
what your FICO score is but don't stress
about it worry about your vantage score
your vantage score is the one that
affects your Equifax Experian and
TransUnion accounts bad credit dispute
everything watch the previous videos on
my channel I explain how to go through
the dispute process don't hire a credit
repair agency all they're going to do
with dispute everything on your credit
report
they're going to do it slowly over the
course of four months minimum they're
going to charge you 100 to 150 hours a
month so that by the end of
you're paying them a minimum of $400 you
can do it yourself in a matter of one
day not even one day but 20 minutes in
front of a computer tape up a letter
there's dispute templates I'll put a
dispute template and it's in the
description of this video
there are dispute templates on both of
the previous videos I've done credit
repair just just fill it out send you
know print three copies send each one in
to the credit each one of those
regretted for euros Equifax Experian and
TransUnion and right away you'll see
your credit score go up because anything
that the creditor isn't actively
reporting or anything that the creditor
doesn't think is worth their time to
respond to the dispute for is going to
be removed from your credit plain and
simple dispute everything see what
sticks and then work from there so watch
the previous videos I go very very far
in depth with how all of that works no
credit now you remember that thing that
we looked at where it shows that there's
the zero heart increase and I'm wanting
too hard inquiries have the same results
so you you can spare up to two hard
inquiries when you start out try to
apply for a Capital One credit card one
of their low end credit cards so to
speak one of the ones that might have a
higher APR but you know a pair doesn't
matter because if you're paying off the
balance in full every month you're not
carrying a balance you don't end up only
in the credit card company anything so
you can go ahead and try to apply with
capital one I heard Capital One is one
of the banks that's more commonly known
for approving people that have a lack of
credit history but if you want to be
safe you want to get a secured credit
card so some other options if you're a
student discover has a student credit
card that you can apply for and they'll
generally approve people who have a
lower or a more thin as they call it
credit history they don't have enough
credit to get a proof or a standard
credit card but you might get a proof or
a student credit card
if you have a checking account that's in
good standings and you've been with a
bank for a significant period of time
especially a credit union a lot of
credit unions can use user discretion
when issuing credit you can get a line
of credit or a credit card with a credit
union just because they know you and
your accounts been in good standings if
you don't have an account with a credit
union get an account with credit union
if you're in track systems you can get
an account with a credit union so that's
another plus right there now all of
those have the risk of denial if you
have a low credit score or no credit
score you're going to risk being denied
the only surefire way to start obtaining
credit is to get a secured credit card
that's forty nine dollars to two hundred
dollars that you put down in order to
get that secured credit card then you
spend that money on that credit card
debt that's your money that you're
borrowing you put two hundred dollars
down and discover in this case because I
need it up on the screen
Discover holds under your two hundred
dollars they keep it unreserved so that
if you rack up a full two hundred dollar
credit limit bill you don't pay off that
$200 then they have collateral to hold
it against that's why it's called
secured credit card you're putting the
two hundred dollars aside to then borrow
from and show the credit card company
that you're capable of paying a credit
card off in full on time and be
responsible with it now a secured credit
card is great because they're gonna
report to the credit bureaus it allows
you to build credit if you have no
credit or bad credit a lot of people
don't want to do that they don't want to
put 49 to two hundred dollars down and
excuse me for a credit card because then
it doesn't feel like a credit card but
you know what you need to start
somewhere and sometimes that's the only
place that you can start now you can get
this drives me crazy but first Premier
Bank you can get a credit card with them
if you have bad credit or
credit but you know what that credit
card is gonna have a $200 activation fee
and a $300 credit limit so after the
$200 activation fee and then the $89
verification fee or whatever the case is
you've already you've already maxed out
that credit card before you spot
anything out in there I know that math
doesn't add up but trust me I got
suckered into that when I was 18 years
old it was very very stupid it's off my
credit report now because I eventually
just had to fork over the cash pay it
off I ended up paying I think like $700
for and I don't know $80 worth of credit
that I actually got to utilize so yeah
you might be able to get an account with
First Premier Bank or Orchard Bank but
those are I mean there's scams I can't
even believe those companies are still
in existence I don't even know if they
are to be honest I hope they're not
because they've been suckering people
for years just don't fall into that trap
what I'm getting at is your money is
much better put into a secured credit
card and then when you close that
secured credit card you get that money
back so get it discovered secured credit
card sometimes you can put $49 down and
get a two hundred dollar limit I mean it
varies it varies depending on the card
the most important thing is to make sure
that your secured credit card doesn't
have an annual fee you don't want an
annual fee and you need to be
responsible with it it's that simple so
let's go through this you put $100 down
let's say and you get $200 on a Discover
secured credit card the discover it card
is a great card great cash back benefits
now you use that card responsibly for a
few months you get by doing so you raise
your credit score up to that six board
you need to apply for a an unsecured
credit card then you go ahead and apply
for a Capital One Platinum card or
discover it you know regular
got an unsecured one even better to do
it with discover if you already have the
secured card with discover because now
discover knows who you are and they see
that you make your payments on time once
you get the unsecured card or the
revolving credit card as it's called
then you can go ahead and close out the
secured credit card better sooner than
later because again let's take a look at
this you want to hang on to that that
credit as long as you can now you don't
want to get to a point where you're nine
years and four months in and you have
$200 on that secured credit card that's
yours and then someday you want that
$200 then actually you close it out and
destroy your average age of credit so
get that out of the way early if you're
going to get a secured credit card get a
regular credit card as soon as you can
and then close out the secured credit
card get your money back and move on
with life it's it's really just that
simple you got to get over the mental
hurt off I don't want to put my own
money up to get a credit card you want
to have to do that that's just how it is
I'm sorry to be the bearer of bad news
but it's a great first stop it's a great
way to start building credit from no
credit or bad credit in fact it's the
second step that you're going to take
after disputing everything that's
currently on your credit report if you
have bad credit the next step is to get
a credit card and use it responsibly if
you can't get an unsecured credit card
you get a secured credit card now
discover it for example I've personally
used that card I like it I actually love
it it's a great card great benefits it
has no annual fee they report monthly
and on the secured card your deposit is
refundable so as I promised some
questions these questions come from
write it I put a post up on reddit our
debt consolidation programs legit or a
scam how does becoming part of one of
these programs mark your credit history
for future credit loan applications now
as far as the second part how do these
credit programs mark your history they
don't do anything your history then no
one is ever going to know that you use a
credit
for a credit repair agency but please
don't use a credit repair agency if
you're considering it send me an email
please just just tell me you need help
I'll help you just don't pay for a
credit repair agency I'm making this
video so that you don't have to pay for
a credit repair agency I believe them to
essentially be scams it depends on your
definition of scam if if scam is you get
ripped off then yeah you're getting
ripped off when you're paying for that
because you can do it yourself much
better and they are going to lie to you
they're going to mislead you they're
going to tell you that they have a
special relationship with the credit
bureaus when in fact they don't the
credit bureaus don't like these people
that's just that's just a fact I mean
these companies our credit bureau is
worst nightmare because they have the
they have to automated documentation
they get information wrong because
they're not the correct party they
flat-out lie they pretend to be you they
write a letter saying I John Smith and
disputing this account they aren't John
Smith you might sign a letter of
representation or a limited power of
attorney but you're not giving them
permission to impersonate you which is
in fact what they then do because a
credit repair agency can't write as a
third party on your behalf so they all
just they they break the law you know
they they impersonate you one the one
that I hired a couple years back which
is still to this day the most popular
one when you type in credit repair
company it's one of the first results on
Google they forged my signature
I mean I'd something for them I actually
signed a document and instead of taking
my signature and putting it on their
documents one of their people just
decided to go ahead and forge my
signature instead it's ridiculous now
they sent it to me instead of TransUnion
by mistake I'm sure it was a clerical
error I opened it off I saw that they
forged my signature I was livid don't
ever use
credit repair agency yes I think they're
scams but you know whatever they if you
use one you might see your credit score
go up but I can assure you that there's
a more effective way to repair your
credit without them what's the best
practice when written communications is
used to establish whether or not an
agency holds that validation how do I
write the latter you're going to want to
watch the the first two videos that I
did I'm gonna link to them below or
maybe I'll use one I card that's up here
or up here or something like that in my
other videos that are referenced in the
description down below I go very much in
depth about that validation if you ask a
collection agency for validation it's
also known as a Dunning notice if a
collection agency calls you ask them for
a validation of that letter I mean again
it's 2018 you're gonna find stuff online
that says it's only valid if they send
it out through the mail you need a
physical copy but these laws and
regulations were put in place a long
time ago and they haven't been updated
in a very long time its 2018 I mean you
do your banking online you really don't
trust a collection agency to send you an
email validation of that letter from my
experience almost all their outgoing
correspondence is digital the consumers
prefer it but there's always that
consumer that uses it as a loophole you
know I want a physical letter signed out
or I'm not paying this and then they
cost us you know fifty cents for a stamp
it's a slight inconvenience and we have
to wait a couple days for the letter to
get to them if you're only gonna deal
with them through written correspondence
I apologize I don't mean to put you down
but that's not the most intelligent way
to deal with a diet especially if it's a
completely legitimate diet keeping lines
of communication open is going to give
you the best possible ability to
negotiate with the agency and prevent
bad you know to prevent them from
reporting things you don't want reported
on your credit report
now if you want to dispute things with
the credit bureaus if you want to make
sure the death legitimate just go ahead
and dispute everything on your credit
report I'm gonna have a template down
below watch my previous videos I explain
how to do that in depth I also saw that
I was gonna give a shout out to these
people first question about the
consolidation agencies being a scam that
is ski for free 900 Miao is the person
that asked about the validation writing
to the agency the one that I just
discussed now view 2000 asked a friend
of mine went to the hospital a few years
back and the bill ended up in
collections the financial assistance
paperwork was done to the hospital a few
months back and the hospital decided to
give a 100% charity discount for the
account can this charity discount letter
be used to remove the collections the
short answer is yes there are companies
that will buy specifically out of stat
medical debt if you're fortunate enough
to have one of those companies purchase
your debt and forgive it they're gonna
send you a letter and you can use that
letter if you have the debt removed from
your credit report if it's still on
there if you have a collection agency
calling you about it go ahead and send
them that letter just make sure the
company that buys and forgives your diet
is a legitimate company company also I
hate to say this but there have been
documented events where companies have
pretended to be charities that buy and
forgive that they do that so that they
get a great deal when they purchase the
debt because they get it much cheaper
than they would if they were buying it
for the purpose of collecting on it then
they go ahead and sell it for a premium
to an agency that then collect on the
debt
just because someone tells you that your
debt has been purchased by a charity and
forgiven make sure you have
documentation that actually verifies
that research the company make sure
they're legitimate especially if you
have a collection agency trying to
collect on the debt side
Dainius li don't trust someone's word
for it make sure you have something in
writing but yes if you have a ladder you
can use that to remove it from I I think
you might ask to remove it from your
credit report yes
removing from collections yes also same
thing send it to the clock change and
see they'll remove it as long as it's
legitimate make sure it has the original
account number it should have the charge
off date it may or may not have that
that's okay it needs to have your name
and needs to have the creditors name and
these thing have the basic information
to verify that it's the same that now a
four a four first I believe is how you
pronounce it so sorry if this is a super
specific question but I have a card that
I was charged that was charged off over
seven years ago which I still have
congratulations I'm not getting a repo
that's insane I've never heard of that
honestly
they never repo'd it I still drive and
use the car an offering the metal paid
off for about forty five hundred dollars
which is the Kelley Blue Book value I
can afford to pay it off how do I do it
without affecting my credit that's
that's fantastic you can afford to pay
it off pay it off but don't pay forty
five hundred dollars if they sent you an
offer for forty five hundred you can get
them to settle for probably twenty two
hundred twenty three hundred dollars
call them on the last business day of
the month when those collectors are in
bonus line as we call it they've already
hit their goal at this point any overage
is going directly towards their bonus
check in some capacity call on the very
last business day of the month say I
have twenty three hundred dollars
available and I'm willing to pay this if
I can get it paid in full today will you
send me something via email stating that
you're willing to accept a twenty three
hundred our settlement today I bet you
that if it's on the last day of the
month and the debt is that old it's
probably out of state at this point as
long as you're not mistaken about when
it was charged off seven years is the
general statute of limitations for most
states
if you have the money to pay it off pay
it off you're saving yourself a lot of
trouble down the line it's it's a
miracle that your car wasn't repo'd
that's great
I assume you got to deal with some
harassing phone calls for a few years
but just get it out of the way get it
over with once you pay it off you can
settle as low as you want but like I
mentioned earlier with my student loans
once they're paid off the collection
agency and the creditor no longer have
any interest in negatively impacting
your credit report dispute the the
dispute that particular item on all of
your credit reports with all the credit
bureaus after it's settled in full I
guarantee they'll remove it that's just
how it works that's how the industry
works so don't worry about how it's
going to impact your credit if it's
seven years old because you're gonna be
able to have removed very easily after
you settle it out if it hasn't already
just fallen off your credit if you have
the money to pay off a dot and you can
settle it go ahead and settle even if
they're not willing to accept $2,300 you
call them during that last week of the
month you're gonna find somebody that's
willing to settle for less than that
forty five hundred which they offered
you and the letter that you received
thanks for providing the awesome service
thank you I appreciate that you
appreciate it
it's crazy that crazy to me that more
people I can't read today it's been a
long two hours here it's really crazy to
me that there's not more people out
there required I can't even read this
they think it's crazy that personal
finance isn't taught in school I think
it's crazy to one world is it that we
live in that they don't have programming
classes and personal finance classes
taught in middle school or high school
at the very least it blows my mind how
many people are uninformed about basic
credit matters when I mean who doesn't
want to be a home owner who doesn't need
a car to drive you need credit credit is
a very important part of life yeah it's
crazy that they don't teach it in school
sorry I can't read that apparently uh
your question I got a new credit card so
I was wondering if it's a good time to
request a credit increase with my
existing cards I've enquired if my
existing cards will perform will perform
a hard or soft poll I've heard though
that multiple HP's which I assume are
hard pulls or hard inquiries and a
14-day period count as a single inquiry
actually that's not true I responded to
you on reddit I think I overlooked that
I apologize I was multitasking trying to
make this video if you receive two or
three hard inquiries in a 14 day window
they all count individually I don't know
who told you that they that they don't
but I'm sorry you were you're
misinformed they're each hard inquiry is
its own hard inquiry regardless of if
you received two in the same day when I
went shopping for auto loans I got hit
with I think four hard inquiries at the
same time because the dealership was
shopping for rates for me even though I
went in there with a pre-approved letter
and said this is the bank that I want my
loan through you know that those auto
companies have deals caught with
specific banks so they're not gonna take
your pre-approval letter and necessarily
go with that so yeah I ended up with
four three or four hard inquiries in one
day for my auto loan it happens it's
unfortunate but it happens now and
that's a fade away would now also be a
good time to request a credit line
increase I assume you mean CLI credit
line increase even if that means a hard
pull or hard inquiry yes
hard inquiry is so much less detrimental
to your credit report than having a good
debt to credit ratio would be or a
percent used
you want to make sure that you have as
much available credit as possible and
you want to use as little of that as
possible a hard inquiry falls off your
credit report after two years sometimes
even less than two years like the effect
of it starts to fade in under two years
so go ahead get all of your hard
inquiries out of the way young and early
so that when you're ready to buy your
house or you want to buy that expensive
car and you don't want to pay a super
high interest rate on it set yourself up
so that the two years has already passed
at that point you want you want hard
inquiries because they don't hurt your
credit score as much as other factors so
if you can trade hard inquiry for a
higher credit line I say go for it
but again it entirely depends on you if
you have one three five or or you know
nine hard inquiries or whatever it was I
forget the numbers it's it's been too
long since I was on that screen I don't
remember I'll talk my head but you know
where your heart inquiries are if you
have one to spare it won't even affect
you if you have several hard inquiries
yeah that that might affect you but in
my opinion it's always better to have a
higher credit line the hard inquiries
will fall off get just get those hard
inquiries out of the way so that two
years from now you're in a better place
but only you know what's truly
beneficial or what's best if you want to
send me a copy of your credit report and
say specifically I intend to buy a house
at this period of time
how will this affect my credit score you
know what don't even send me your credit
report although I am willing and more
than happy to help anyone that has any
questions but they have they have tools
where you can simulate your credit
report you could put in what your
current credit score is assert something
like credit credit repair a hypothetical
hypothetical tool I that's not what it's
called credit simulation - all there you
go
you can figure out how it's going to
impact your credit score now keep in
mind that even though
TransUnion Equifax and Experian all use
VantageScore they don't all use it the
exact same way so your results are going
to vary from creditor from Bureau to
Bureau but you can get a good general
idea of it because the Vantage score is
pretty well understood although its
proprietary no one knows for sure except
the vantage score people but a lot of
people have a good enough understanding
of it to be able to create algorithms
that represent it to a similar enough
fashion that you can use these online
tools to figure out if it's in your best
interest you take a heart inquiry and
obtain a larger credit credit line or if
that heart inquiry is going to be
disasters for you which is usually zero
percent of the time hard inquiries are
not a big deal if we go back to the
other slide it is the lowest you know
the lowest thing you need to worry about
it's a very very I'm sorry I'm burned
out I hope you guys got some good
information that last credit that last
question comes to us from Parker L ass
so let me know if you have any
additional questions and yeah that was
it so thank you for watching let me know
what additional questions you might have
good luck with your credit and I'm more
than happy to help feel free to
subscribe and click the notification
button so you're notified when I put out
additional videos go ahead and ask as
many questions as you want you're gonna
all you're gonna do is give me some more
material to make future videos off of
thanks for watching go ahead and get it
give it a thumbs up if you enjoyed this
video
I completely forgot I told you guys I
was going to show you what a that
portfolio looks like so that you know
what the clock what information the
collection agencies have keep in mind
this is all false information none of
this
what you're about to see is fake names
fake social security numbers fake
addresses fake phone numbers it doesn't
mean that the phone number doesn't
belong to someone that doesn't mean that
the social doesn't belong to someone or
that that name doesn't belong to someone
but the information that you're about to
see is all 100% fabricated so you're not
gonna be able to steal someone's
identity with this information so don't
even try plus it's a scummy thing to try
anyways but this is all completely
fabricated I want to make that perfectly
clear clear before I switch over to it
now this is what a debt portfolio looks
like when a collection agency receives
it you've got the account number first
name last name social Ekho city state or
in this case county city state zip phone
number you know home phone cell phone
employer work phone email address
account type creditor open date charge
off date bank name account number
I'm sorry voting under account number
return reason which is account frozen
stop payment account closed insufficient
funds stopped payment whatever I'm just
repeating myself now um check date that
could also be delinquency day it also
depends on what type of debt it is if
it's a credit card you're not gonna have
you're not gonna have a delinquency date
but the charge off date is going to be
the delinquency date the open date and
the charge off date might be ten years
apart on a credit card if you kept it in
good standings for several years but
this this particular fake portfolio or
mock portfolio is a personal loan like a
payday loan or installment loan at that
consolidation loan something like that
you've got the last payment date the
last payment amount the original balance
the principal the turns off principle
ass off fees that's non-sufficient funds
accrued interest current balance
reference name reference phone number
you might have some other fields you
might have something like credit score
for example so ignore this you're not
seeing this right now
just forgot Tennessee's here what say
490 and 850 yeah I got a typo there
sweatin alright so now we got some
credit scores on here too
no collection agency like me you might
want to sort the accounts by the credit
score largest to smallest and past the
accounts out first so first and foremost
you're working Deana luge's account
because she's got that perfect 850
credit score that wise and then the next
count that's gonna be called is Virgie
keel now most agencies don't actually
work that way and most collection
agencies don't actually have a credit
score they have what's called a recovery
score which is similar to a credit score
but it's based off of your repayment
history instead of your the factors that
your credit report is based off of so
again this is all completely fictional
fabricated information I did this just
to show you what a debt portfolio it
looks like so you know that when your
account has been purchased by a
collection agency this is what it looks
like if this was actually at that
portfolio this particular portfolio
would be for example and I hope you guys
find this interesting that's why I'm
showing you that is three hundred and
forty-three dollars I'm sorry three
three hundred forty three thousand two
hundred forty-one dollars now let's say
that it's a zero agency portfolio it's
brand-new let's say that the agency is
paying twelve cents on the dollar for
this debt so that debt portfolio of was
this five hundred accounts my camera is
covering the screen I can't see five
hundred accounts so they're paying
forty-one thousand dollars for these
five hundred accounts so
so curiosity the average balance would
be not every chance the cost per account
would be eighty-two dollars
the agency each one of these accounts is
worth eighty two dollars and 38 cents to
that collection agency that purchased
this debt now Clark James since he's
only liquidate anywhere you know we'll
say around ten to twenty percent per
portfolio so the majority of people
don't pay the first agency which is why
that is place or sold so many times
until until they get it down to just the
you know pardon me for saying this the
deadbeats the losers the people who have
no intention to pay no matter how many
times you prove them that they owe the
die and those are the people that need
to be sued to get their money but take
care of your that's early don't let it
get to those low level collection
agencies that you hear the negative
reports by on the news that are just
purchasing information online
it looks like this they you know they
don't care they don't care if the
informations accurate or not they're
gonna try to collect on it you know
licenses are expensive my agencies
license but you know we we only operate
in certain states because certain
licenses are very expensive some
agencies operate in any state they want
to regardless of whether or not they're
licensed you know that that's the way
the industry can be sometimes so if
you're paying off the debt with that
first agency that calls you instead of
the fifth one you have you know you're
dealing with the legitimate guys and not
the bad apples so that's that pay your
bills view your credit reports verify
the information and get that perfect 850
thanks for watching